<?xml version="1.0" encoding="UTF-8"?><?xml-stylesheet href="graphics-support-documents/rules.xsl" type="text/xsl"?><?xml-stylesheet href="graphics-support-documents/rules.css" type="text/css"?><document xmlns="http://xml.house.gov/schemas/uslm/1.0">
  <meta xmlns:dc="http://purl.org/dc/elements/1.1/">
    <dc:title>Rule XXVI: Financial Disclosure</dc:title>
    <property name="s-heading" idref="rule-XXVI-1">§1103. Financial report disclosing certain financial interests.</property>
  </meta>
  <content>
    <level id="rule-XXVI" name="rule">
      <num value="XXVI">Rule XXVI</num>
      <heading>Financial Disclosure</heading>
      <clause id="rule-XXVI-1">
        <num value="1">1.</num>
        <p id="s1103">The Clerk shall send a copy of each report filed with the Clerk under title I of the Ethics in Government Act of 1978 within the seven-day period beginning on the date on which the report is filed to the Committee on Ethics.</p>
      </clause>
      <clause id="rule-XXVI-2">
        <num value="2">2.</num>
        <p>For the purposes of this rule, the provisions of title I of the Ethics in Government Act of 1978 shall be considered Rules of the House as they pertain to Members, Delegates, the Resident Commissioner, officers, and employees of the House.</p>
      </clause>
      <clause id="rule-XXVI-3">
        <num value="3">3.</num>
        <p>Members of the board of the Office of Congressional Ethics shall file annual financial disclosure reports with the Clerk of the House on or before May 15 of each calendar year after any year in which they perform the duties of that position. Such reports shall be on a form prepared by the Clerk that is substantially similar to form 450 of the Office of Government Ethics. The Clerk shall send a copy of each such report filed with the Clerk within the seven-day period beginning on the date on which the report is filed to the Committee on Ethics and shall have them printed as a House document and made available to the public by August 1 of each year.</p>
      </clause>
      <note>
        <p>The original version of this rule (formerly rule XLIV) was adopted in the 90th Congress, in the same resolution that redefined the jurisdiction of the Committee on Standards of Official Conduct (now Ethics) (H. Res. 1099, Apr. 3, 1968, p. 8803). In the 91st Congress the rule was amended, effective for years after 1970, to require public disclosure of: (1) honoraria from a single source totaling $300 or more; and (2) each creditor to whom was owed an unsecured loan or other indebtedness of $10,000 or more outstanding for at least 90 days in the preceding calendar year (H. Res. 796, May 26, 1970, p. 17019). It was further amended in the 92d Congress to bring the Delegates and Resident Commissioner within the definition of “Members” in the final sentence of the rule (H. Res. 5, Jan. 22, 1971, p. 144; H. Res. 1153, Oct. 13, 1972, pp. 36021–23), and was amended in the 95th Congress to delete an obsolete reference (H. Res. 5, Jan. 4, 1977, pp. 53–70). The rule was completely amended in the 95th Congress, effective July 1, 1977, to: (1) broaden the sources and minimum amounts of income reported; (2) require reports to be filed with the Clerk as well as with the Committee on Standards of Official Conduct; and (3) make reports available to the public as printed House documents rather than having them maintained by the Committee on Standards of Official Conduct (H. Res. 287, Mar. 2, 1977, pp. 5933–53), but this last requirement was repealed in the 113th Congress (sec. 2(f), H. Res. 5, Jan. 3, 2013, p. __). The rule was again amended in the 96th Congress to incorporate by reference the relevant provisions of title I of the Ethics in Government Act of 1978 as they pertain to Members, officers, and employees of the House (H. Res. 5, Jan. 15, 1979, pp. 7–16). Clause 1 was amended by the Ethics Reform Act of 1989 to make conforming changes in certain dates (P.L. 101–194). Before the House recodified its rules in the 106th Congress, this provision was found in former rule XLIV (H. Res. 5, Jan. 6, 1999, p. 47). This rule was redesignated as rule XXVI in the 107th Congress (sec. 2(s), H. Res. 5, Jan. 3, 2001, p. 24). Clause 3 was added in the 110th Congress (H. Res. 895, Mar. 11, 2008, p. 3743). A gender-based reference was eliminated in the 111th Congress (sec. 2(l), H. Res. 5, Jan. 6, 2009, p. 7). This rule was amended in the 112th Congress to reflect a change in committee name (sec. 2(e)(8), H. Res. 5, Jan. 5, 2011, p. 80). Clause 3 was amended in the 114th Congress to replace an archaic reference to clause 1 with an August 1 deadline (sec. 2(h), H. Res. 5, Jan. 6, 2015, p. __).</p>
        <p>For an in-depth discussion of this rule prepared by the Committee on Standards of Official Conduct (now Ethics), see the <i>House Ethics Manual</i> (110th Cong., 2d Sess.). For a requirement that the Clerk make financial disclosure reports available to the public in electronic form, see section 8 of the Stop Trading on Congressional Knowledge Act of 2012 (P.L. 112–105, as amended by P.L. 113–7).</p>
        <p class="full-space-above">Pertinent provisions of title I of the Ethics in Government Act of 1978 (5 U.S.C. App. 101–111) follow:</p>
        <quotedContent class="usc">
          <title>
            <num value="I">Title I—</num>
            <heading>Financial Disclosure Requirements of Federal Personnel</heading>
            <crossHeading>persons required to file</crossHeading>
            <section>
              <num value="101">Sec. 101.</num>
              <subsection>
                <num value="a">(a)</num>
                <p>Within thirty days of assuming the position of an officer or employee described in subsection (f), an individual shall file a report containing the information described in section 102(b) unless the individual has left another position described in subsection (f) within thirty days prior to assuming such new position or has already filed a report under this title with respect to nomination for the new position or as a candidate for the position.</p>
              </subsection>
              <text class="three-star">* * *</text>
              <subsection>
                <num value="c">(c)</num>
                <p>Within thirty days of becoming a candidate as defined in section 301 of the Federal Campaign Act of 1971, in a calendar year for nomination or election to the office of President, Vice President, or Member of Congress, or on or before May 15 of that calendar year, whichever is later, but in no event later than 30 days before the election, and on or before May 15 of each successive year an individual continues to be a candidate, an individual other than an incumbent President, Vice President, or Member of Congress shall file a report containing the information described in section 102(b). Notwithstanding the preceding sentence, in any calendar year in which an individual continues to be a candidate for any office but all elections for such office relating to such candidacy were held in prior calendar years, such individual need not file a report unless he becomes a candidate for another vacancy in that office or another office during that year.</p>
              </subsection>
              <subsection>
                <num value="d">(d)</num>
                <p>Any individual who is an officer or employee described in subsection (f) during any calendar year and performs the duties of his position or office for a period in excess of sixty days in that calendar year shall file on or before May 15 of the succeeding year a report containing the information described in section 102(a).</p>
              </subsection>
              <subsection>
                <num value="e">(e)</num>
                <p>Any individual who occupies a position described in subsection (f) shall, on or before the thirtieth day after termination of employment in such position, file a report containing the information described in section 102(a) covering the preceding calendar year if the report required by subsection (d) has not been filed and covering the portion of the calendar year in which such termination occurs up to the date the individual left such office or position, unless such individual has accepted employment in another position described in subsection (f).</p>
              </subsection>
              <subsection>
                <num value="f">(f)</num>
                <chapeau>The officers and employees referred to in subsections (a), (d), and (e) are— <inline name="three-star">* * *</inline>
                        </chapeau>
                <paragraph>
                  <num value="9">(9)</num>
                  <p>a Member of Congress as defined under section 109(12);</p>
                </paragraph>
                <paragraph>
                  <num value="10">(10)</num>
                  <p>an officer or employee of the Congress as defined under section 109(13);</p>
                </paragraph>
                <text class="three-star">* * *</text>
              </subsection>
              <subsection>
                <num value="g">(g)</num><paragraph><num value="1">(1)</num>
                  <p>Reasonable extensions of time for filing any report may be granted under procedures prescribed by the supervising ethics office for each branch, but the total of such extensions shall not exceed ninety days. <inline name="three-star">* * *</inline>
                           </p>
                </paragraph>
              </subsection>
              <subsection>
                <num value="h">(h)</num>
                <chapeau>The provisions of subsections (a), (b), and (e) shall not apply to an individual who, as determined by the designated agency ethics official or Secretary concerned (or in the case of a Presidential appointee under subsection (b), the Director of the Office of Government Ethics), the congressional ethics committees, or the Judicial Conference, is not reasonably expected to perform the duties of his office or position for more than sixty days in a calendar year, except that if such individual performs the duties of his office or position for more than sixty days in a calendar year—</chapeau>
                <paragraph>
                  <num value="1">(1)</num>
                  <p>the report required by subsections (a) and (b) shall be filed within fifteen days of the sixtieth day, and</p>
                </paragraph>
                <paragraph>
                  <num value="2">(2)</num>
                  <p>the report required by subsection (e) shall be filed as provided in such subsection.</p>
                </paragraph>
              </subsection>
              <subsection>
                <num value="i">(i)</num>
                <chapeau>The supervising ethics office for each branch may grant a publicly available request for a waiver of any reporting requirement under this section for an individual who is expected to perform or has performed the duties of his office or position less than one hundred and thirty days in a calendar year, but only if the supervising ethics office determines that—</chapeau>
                <paragraph>
                  <num value="1">(1)</num>
                  <p>such individual is not a full-time employee of the Government,</p>
                </paragraph>
                <paragraph>
                  <num value="2">(2)</num>
                  <p>such individual is able to provide services specially needed by the Government,</p>
                </paragraph>
                <paragraph>
                  <num value="3">(3)</num>
                  <p>it is unlikely that the individual’s outside employment or financial interests will create a conflict of interest, and</p>
                </paragraph>
                <paragraph>
                  <num value="4">(4)</num>
                  <p>public financial disclosure by such individual is not necessary in the circumstances.</p>
                </paragraph>
              </subsection>
            </section>
            <crossHeading>contents of reports</crossHeading>
            <section>
              <num value="102">Sec. 102.</num>
              <subsection>
                <num value="a">(a)</num>
                <chapeau>Each report filed pursuant to section 101 (d) and (e) shall include a full and complete statement with respect to the following:</chapeau>
                <paragraph>
                  <num value="1">(1)</num><subparagraph><num value="A">(A)</num>
                    <p>The source, type, and amount or value of income (other than income referred to in subparagraph (B)) from any source (other than from current employment by the United States Government), and the source, date, and amount of honoraria from any source, received during the preceding calendar year, aggregating $200 or more in value and, effective January 1, 1991, the source, date, and amount of payments made to charitable organizations in lieu of honoraria, and the reporting individual shall simultaneously file with the applicable supervising ethics office, on a confidential basis, a corresponding list of recipients of all such payments, together with the dates and amounts of such payments.</p>
                  </subparagraph>
                  <subparagraph>
                    <num value="B">(B)</num>
                    <chapeau>The source and type of income which consists of dividends, rents, interest, and capital gains, received during the preceding calendar year which exceeds $200 in amount or value, and an indication of which of the following categories the amount or value of such item of income is within:</chapeau>
                    <clause>
                      <num value="i">(i)</num>
                      <p>not more than $1,000,</p>
                    </clause>
                    <clause>
                      <num value="ii">(ii)</num>
                      <p>greater than $1,000 but not more than $2,500,</p>
                    </clause>
                    <clause>
                      <num value="iii">(iii)</num>
                      <p>greater than $2,500 but not more than $5,000,</p>
                    </clause>
                    <clause>
                      <num value="iv">(iv)</num>
                      <p>greater than $5,000 but not more than $15,000,</p>
                    </clause>
                    <clause>
                      <num value="v">(v)</num>
                      <p>greater than $15,000 but not more than $50,000,</p>
                    </clause>
                    <clause>
                      <num value="vi">(vi)</num>
                      <p>greater than $50,000 but not more than $100,000,</p>
                    </clause>
                    <clause>
                      <num value="vii">(vii)</num>
                      <p>greater than $100,000 but not more than $1,000,000,</p>
                    </clause>
                    <clause>
                      <num value="viii">(viii)</num>
                      <p>greater than $1,000,000 but not more than $5,000,000, or</p>
                    </clause>
                    <clause>
                      <num value="ix">(ix)</num>
                      <p>greater than $5,000,000.</p>
                    </clause>
                  </subparagraph>
                </paragraph>
                <paragraph>
                  <num value="2">(2)</num><subparagraph><num value="A">(A)</num>
                    <p>The identity of the source, a brief description, and the value of all gifts aggregating more than the minimal value as established by section 7342(a)(5) of title 5, United States Code, or $250, whichever is greater, received from any source other than a relative of the reporting individual during the preceding calendar year, except that any food, lodging, or entertainment received as personal hospitality of an individual need not be reported, and any gift with a fair market value of $100 or less, as adjusted at the same time and by the same percentage as the minimal value is adjusted, need not be aggregated for purposes of this subparagraph.</p>
                  </subparagraph>
                  <subparagraph>
                    <num value="B">(B)</num>
                    <p>The identity of the source and a brief description (including a travel itinerary, dates, and nature of expenses provided) of reimbursements received from any source aggregating more than the minimal value as established by section 7342(a)(5) of title 5, United States Code, or $250, whichever is greater, and received during the preceding calendar year.</p>
                  </subparagraph>
                  <subparagraph>
                    <num value="C">(C)</num>
                    <p>In an unusual case, a gift need not be aggregated under subparagraph (A) if a publicly available request for a waiver is granted.</p>
                  </subparagraph>
                </paragraph>
                <paragraph>
                  <num value="3">(3)</num>
                  <p>The identity and category of value of any interest in property held during the preceding calendar year in a trade or business, or for investment or the production of income, which has a fair market value which exceeds $1,000 as of the close of the preceding calendar year, excluding any personal liability owed to the reporting individual by a spouse, or by a parent, brother, sister, or child of the reporting individual or of the reporting individual’s spouse, or any deposits aggregating $5,000 or less in a personal savings account. For purposes of this paragraph, a personal savings account shall include any certificate of deposit or any other form of deposit in a bank, savings and loan association, credit union, or similar financial institution.</p>
                </paragraph>
                <paragraph>
                  <num value="4">(4)</num>
                  <chapeau>The identity and category of value of the total liabilities owed to any creditor other than a spouse, or a parent, brother, sister, or child of the reporting individual or of the reporting individual’s spouse which exceed $10,000 at any time during the preceding calendar year, excluding—</chapeau>
                  <subparagraph>
                    <num value="A">(A)</num>
                    <chapeau>any mortgage secured by real property which is a personal residence of the reporting individual or his spouse, except that this exception shall not apply to a reporting individual—</chapeau>
                    <clause>
                      <num value="i">(i)</num>
                      <p>described in paragraph (1), (2), or (9) of section 101(f);</p>
                    </clause>
                    <clause>
                      <num value="ii">(ii)</num>
                      <chapeau>described in section 101(b) who has been nominated for appointment as an officer or employee in the executive branch described in subsection (f) of such section, other than—</chapeau>
                      <subclause>
                        <num value="I">(I)</num>
                        <chapeau>an individual appointed to a position—</chapeau>
                        <item>
                          <num value="aa">(aa)</num>
                          <p>as a Foreign Service Officer below the rank of ambassador; or</p>
                        </item>
                        <item>
                          <num value="bb">(bb)</num>
                          <p>in the uniformed services for which the pay grade prescribed by section 201 of title 37, United States Code is O-6 or below; or</p>
                        </item>
                      </subclause>
                      <subclause>
                        <num value="II">(II)</num>
                        <p>a special government employee, as defined under section 202 of title 18, United States Code; or</p>
                      </subclause>
                    </clause>
                    <clause>
                      <num value="iii">(iii)</num>
                      <chapeau>described in section 101(f) who is in a position in the executive branch the appointment to which is made by the President and requires advice and consent of the Senate, other than—</chapeau>
                      <subclause>
                        <num value="I">(I)</num>
                        <chapeau>an individual appointed to a position—</chapeau>
                        <item>
                          <num value="aa">(aa)</num>
                          <p>as a Foreign Service Officer below the rank of ambassador; or</p>
                        </item>
                        <item>
                          <num value="bb">(bb)</num>
                          <p>in the uniformed services for which the pay grade prescribed by section 201 of title 37, United States Code is O-6 or below; or</p>
                        </item>
                      </subclause>
                      <subclause>
                        <num value="II">(II)</num>
                        <p>a special government employee, as defined under section 202 of title 18, United States Code; and</p>
                      </subclause>
                    </clause>
                  </subparagraph>
                  <subparagraph>
                    <num value="B">(B)</num>
                    <p>any loan secured by a personal motor vehicle, household furniture, or appliances, which loan does not exceed the purchase price of the item which secures it.</p>
                  </subparagraph>
                  <continuation>With respect to revolving charge accounts, only those with an outstanding liability which exceeds $10,000 as of the close of the preceding calendar year need be reported under this paragraph.</continuation>
                </paragraph>
                <paragraph>
                  <num value="5">(5)</num>
                  <chapeau>Except as provided in this paragraph, a brief description, the date, and category of value of any purchase, sale or exchange during the preceding calendar year exceeds $1,000—</chapeau>
                  <subparagraph>
                    <num value="A">(A)</num>
                    <p>in real property, other than property used solely as a personal residence of the reporting individual or his spouse; or</p>
                  </subparagraph>
                  <subparagraph>
                    <num value="B">(B)</num>
                    <p>in stocks, bonds, commodities futures, and other forms of securities.</p>
                  </subparagraph>
                  <continuation>Reporting is not required under this paragraph of any transaction solely by and between the reporting individual, his spouse, or dependent children.</continuation>
                </paragraph>
                <paragraph>
                  <num value="6">(6)</num><subparagraph><num value="A">(A)</num>
                    <p>The identity of all positions held on or before the date of filing during the current calendar year (and, for the first report filed by an individual, during the two-year period preceding such calendar year) as an officer, director, trustee, partner, proprietor, representative, employee, or consultant of any corporation, company, firm, partnership, or other business enterprise, any nonprofit organization, any labor organization, or any educational or other institution other than the United States. This subparagraph shall not require the reporting of positions held in any religious, social, fraternal, or political entity and positions solely of an honorary nature.</p>
                  </subparagraph>
                  <subparagraph>
                    <num value="B">(B)</num>
                    <chapeau>If any person, other than the United States Government, paid a nonelected reporting individual compensation in excess of $5,000 in any of the two calendar years prior to the calendar year during which the individual files his first report under this title, the individual shall include in the report—</chapeau>
                    <clause>
                      <num value="i">(i)</num>
                      <p>the identity of each source of such compensation; and</p>
                    </clause>
                    <clause>
                      <num value="ii">(ii)</num>
                      <p>a brief description of the nature of the duties performed or services rendered by the reporting individual for each such source.</p>
                    </clause>
                    <continuation>The preceding sentence shall not require any individual to include in such report any information which is considered confidential as a result of a privileged relationship, established by law, between such individual and any person nor shall it require an individual to report any information with respect to any person for whom services were provided by any firm or association of which such individual was a member, partner, or employee unless such individual was directly involved in the provision of such services.</continuation>
                  </subparagraph>
                </paragraph>
                <paragraph>
                  <num value="7">(7)</num>
                  <p>A description of the date, parties to, and terms of any agreement or arrangement with respect to (A) future employment; (B) a leave of absence during the period of the reporting individual’s Government service; (C) continuation of payments by a former employer other than the United States Government; and (D) continuing participation in an employee welfare or benefit plan maintained by a former employer.</p>
                </paragraph>
                <paragraph>
                  <num value="8">(8)</num>
                  <p>The category of the total cash value of any interest of the reporting individual in a qualified blind trust, unless the trust instrument was executed prior to July 24, 1995 and precludes the beneficiary from receiving information on the total cash value of any interest in the qualified blind trust.</p>
                </paragraph>
              </subsection>
              <subsection>
                <num value="b">(b)</num><paragraph><num value="1">(1)</num>
                  <chapeau>Each report filed pursuant to subsections (a), (b), and (c) of section 101 shall include a full and complete statement with respect to the information required by—</chapeau>
                  <subparagraph>
                    <num value="A">(A)</num>
                    <p>paragraph (1) of subsection (a) for the year of filing and the preceding calendar year,</p>
                  </subparagraph>
                  <subparagraph>
                    <num value="B">(B)</num>
                    <p>paragraphs (3) and (4) of subsection (a) as of the date specified in the report but which is less than thirty-one days before the filing date, and</p>
                  </subparagraph>
                  <subparagraph>
                    <num value="C">(C)</num>
                    <p>paragraphs (6) and (7) of subsection (a) as of the filing date but for periods described in such paragraphs.</p>
                  </subparagraph>
                </paragraph>
                <paragraph>
                  <num value="2">(2)</num><subparagraph><num value="A">(A)</num>
                    <p>In lieu of filling out one or more schedules of a financial disclosure form, an individual may supply the required information in an alternative format, pursuant to either rules adopted by the supervising ethics office for the branch in which such individual serves or pursuant to a specific written determination by such office for a reporting individual.</p>
                  </subparagraph>
                  <subparagraph>
                    <num value="B">(B)</num>
                    <p>In lieu of indicating the category of amount or value of any item contained in any report filed under this title, a reporting individual may indicate the exact dollar amount of such item.</p>
                  </subparagraph>
                </paragraph>
              </subsection>
              <subsection>
                <num value="c">(c)</num>
                <p>In the case of any individual described in section 101(e), any reference to the preceding calendar year shall be considered also to include that part of the calendar year of filing up to the date of the termination of employment.</p>
              </subsection>
              <subsection>
                <num value="d">(d)</num><paragraph><num value="1">(1)</num>
                  <chapeau>The categories for reporting the amount or value of the items covered in paragraphs (3), (4), (5), and (8) of subsection (a) are as follows:</chapeau>
                  <subparagraph>
                    <num value="A">(A)</num>
                    <p>not more than $15,000;</p>
                  </subparagraph>
                  <subparagraph>
                    <num value="B">(B)</num>
                    <p>greater than $15,000 but not more than $50,000;</p>
                  </subparagraph>
                  <subparagraph>
                    <num value="C">(C)</num>
                    <p>greater than $50,000 but not more than $100,000;</p>
                  </subparagraph>
                  <subparagraph>
                    <num value="D">(D)</num>
                    <p>greater than $100,000 but not more than $250,000;</p>
                  </subparagraph>
                  <subparagraph>
                    <num value="E">(E)</num>
                    <p>greater than $250,000 but not more than $500,000;</p>
                  </subparagraph>
                  <subparagraph>
                    <num value="F">(F)</num>
                    <p>greater than $500,000 but not more than $1,000,000;</p>
                  </subparagraph>
                  <subparagraph>
                    <num value="G">(G)</num>
                    <p>greater than $1,000,000 but not more than $5,000,000;</p>
                  </subparagraph>
                  <subparagraph>
                    <num value="H">(H)</num>
                    <p>greater than $5,000,000 but not more than $25,000,000;</p>
                  </subparagraph>
                  <subparagraph>
                    <num value="I">(I)</num>
                    <p>greater than $25,000,000 but not more than $50,000,000; and</p>
                  </subparagraph>
                  <subparagraph>
                    <num value="J">(J)</num>
                    <p>greater than $50,000,000.</p>
                  </subparagraph>
                </paragraph>
                <paragraph>
                  <num value="2">(2)</num>
                  <p>For the purposes of paragraph (3) of subsection (a) if the current value of an interest in real property (or an interest in a real estate partnership) is not ascertainable without an appraisal, an individual may list (A) the date of purchase and the purchase price of the interest in the real property, or (B) the assessed value of the real property for tax purposes, adjusted to reflect the market value of the property used for the assessment if the assessed value is computed at less than 100 percent of such market value, but such individual shall include in his report a full and complete description of the method used to determine such assessed value, instead of specifying a category of value pursuant to paragraph (1) of this subsection. If the current value of any other item required to be reported under paragraph (3) of subsection (a) is not ascertainable without an appraisal, such individual may list the book value of a corporation whose stock is not publicly traded, the net worth of a business partnership, the equity value of an individually owned business, or with respect to other holdings, any recognized indication of value, but such individual shall include in his report a full and complete description of the method used in determining such value. In lieu of any value referred to in the preceding sentence, an individual may list the assessed value of the item for tax purposes, adjusted to reflect the market value of the item used for the assessment if the assessed value is computed at less than 100 percent of such market value, but a full and complete description of the method used in determining such assessed value shall be included in the report.</p>
                </paragraph>
              </subsection>
              <subsection>
                <num value="e">(e)</num><paragraph><num value="1">(1)</num>
                  <chapeau>Except as provided in the last sentence of this paragraph, each report required by section 101 shall also contain information listed in paragraphs (1) through (5) of subsection (a) of this section respecting the spouse or dependent child of the reporting individual as follows:</chapeau>
                  <subparagraph>
                    <num value="A">(A)</num>
                    <p>The source of items of earned income earned by a spouse from any person which exceed $1,000 and the source and amount of any honoraria received by a spouse, except that, with respect to earned income (other than honoraria), if the spouse is self-employed in business or a profession, only the nature of such business or profession need be reported.</p>
                  </subparagraph>
                  <subparagraph>
                    <num value="B">(B)</num>
                    <p>All information required to be reported in subsection (a)(1)(B) with respect to income derived by a spouse or dependent child from any asset held by the spouse or dependent child and reported pursuant to subsection (a)(3).</p>
                  </subparagraph>
                  <subparagraph>
                    <num value="C">(C)</num>
                    <p>In the case of any gifts received by a spouse or dependent child which are not received totally independent of the relationship of the spouse or dependent child to the reporting individual, the identity of the source and a brief description of gifts of transportation, lodging, food, or entertainment and a brief description and the value of other gifts.</p>
                  </subparagraph>
                  <subparagraph>
                    <num value="D">(D)</num>
                    <p>In the case of any reimbursements received by a spouse or dependent child which are not received totally independent of the relationship of the spouse or dependent child to the reporting individual, the identity of the source and a brief description of each such reimbursement.</p>
                  </subparagraph>
                  <subparagraph>
                    <num value="E">(E)</num>
                    <p>In the case of items described in paragraphs (3) through (5) of subsection (a), all information required to be reported under these paragraphs other than items (i) which the reporting individual certifies represent the spouse’s or dependent child’s sole financial interest or responsibility and which the reporting individual has no knowledge of, (ii) which are not in any way, past or present, derived from the income, assets, or activities of the reporting individual, and (iii) from which the reporting individual neither derives, nor expects to derive, any financial or economic benefit.</p>
                  </subparagraph>
                  <subparagraph>
                    <num value="F">(F)</num>
                    <p>For purposes of this section, categories with amounts or values greater than $1,000,000 set forth in sections 102(a)(1)(B) and 102(d)(1) shall apply to the income, assets, or liabilities of spouses and dependent children only if the income, assets, or liabilities are held jointly with the reporting individual. All other income, assets, or liabilities of the spouse or dependent children required to be reported under this section in an amount or value greater than $1,000,000 shall be categorized only as an amount or value greater than $1,000,000.</p>
                  </subparagraph>
                  <continuation>Reports required by subsections (a), (b), and (c) of section 101 shall, with respect to the spouse and dependent child of the reporting individual, only contain information listed in paragraphs (1), (3), and (4) of subsection (a), as specified in this paragraph.</continuation>
                </paragraph>
                <paragraph>
                  <num value="2">(2)</num>
                  <p>No report shall be required with respect to a spouse living separate and apart from the reporting individual with the intention of terminating the marriage or providing for permanent separation; or with respect to any income or obligations of an individual arising from the dissolution of his marriage or the permanent separation from his spouse.</p>
                </paragraph>
              </subsection>
              <subsection>
                <num value="f">(f)</num><paragraph><num value="1">(1)</num>
                  <p>Except as provided in paragraph (2), each reporting individual shall report the information required to be reported pursuant to subsections (a), (b), and (c) of this section with respect to the holdings of and the income from a trust or other financial arrangement from which income is received by, or with respect to which a beneficial interest in principal or income is held by, such individual, his spouse, or any dependent child.</p>
                </paragraph>
                <paragraph>
                  <num value="2">(2)</num>
                  <chapeau>A reporting individual need not report the holdings of or the source of income from any of the holdings of—</chapeau>
                  <subparagraph>
                    <num value="A">(A)</num>
                    <p>any qualified blind trust (as defined in paragraph (3));</p>
                  </subparagraph>
                  <subparagraph>
                    <num value="B">(B)</num>
                    <chapeau>a trust—</chapeau>
                    <clause>
                      <num value="i">(i)</num>
                      <p>which was not created directly by such individual, his spouse, or any dependent child, and</p>
                    </clause>
                    <clause>
                      <num value="ii">(ii)</num>
                      <p>the holdings or sources of income of which such individual, his spouse, and any dependent child have no knowledge of; or</p>
                    </clause>
                  </subparagraph>
                  <subparagraph>
                    <num value="C">(C)</num>
                    <p>an entity described under the provisions of paragraph (8), but such individual shall report the category of the amount of income received by him, his spouse, or any dependent child from the trust or other entity under subsection (a)(1)(B) of this section.</p>
                  </subparagraph>
                </paragraph>
                <paragraph>
                  <num value="3">(3)</num>
                  <chapeau>For purpose of this subsection, the term “qualified blind trust” includes any trust in which a reporting individual, his spouse, or any minor or dependent child has a beneficial interest in the principal or income, and which meets the following requirements:</chapeau>
                  <subparagraph>
                    <num value="A">(A)</num><clause><num value="i">(i)</num>
                      <chapeau>The trustee of the trust and any other entity designated in the trust instrument to perform fiduciary duties is a financial institution, an attorney, a certified public accountant, a broker, or an investment advisor who—</chapeau>
                      <subclause>
                        <num value="I">(I)</num>
                        <p>is independent of and not associated with any interested party so that the trustee or other person cannot be controlled or influenced in the administration of the trust by any interested party;</p>
                      </subclause>
                      <subclause>
                        <num value="II">(II)</num>
                        <p>is not and has not been an employee of or affiliated with any interested party and is not a partner of, or involved in any joint venture or other investment with, any interested party; and</p>
                      </subclause>
                      <subclause>
                        <num value="III">(III)</num>
                        <p>is not a relative of any interested party.</p>
                      </subclause>
                    </clause>
                    <clause>
                      <num value="ii">(ii)</num>
                      <chapeau>Any officer or employee of a trustee or other entity who is involved in the management or control of the trust—</chapeau>
                      <subclause>
                        <num value="I">(I)</num>
                        <p>is independent of and not associated with any interested party so that such officer or employee cannot be controlled or influenced in the administration of the trust by any interested party;</p>
                      </subclause>
                      <subclause>
                        <num value="II">(II)</num>
                        <p>is not a partner of, or involved in any joint venture or other investment with, any interested party; and</p>
                      </subclause>
                      <subclause>
                        <num value="III">(III)</num>
                        <p>is not a relative of any interested party.</p>
                      </subclause>
                    </clause>
                  </subparagraph>
                  <subparagraph>
                    <num value="B">(B)</num>
                    <p>Any asset transferred to the trust by an interested party is free of any restriction with respect to its transfer or sale unless such restriction is expressly approved by the supervising ethics office of the reporting individual.</p>
                  </subparagraph>
                  <subparagraph>
                    <num value="C">(C)</num>
                    <chapeau>The trust instrument which establishes the trust provides that—</chapeau>
                    <clause>
                      <num value="i">(i)</num>
                      <p>except to the extent provided in subparagraph (B) of this paragraph, the trustee in the exercise of his authority and discretion to manage and control the assets of the trust shall not consult or notify any interested party;</p>
                    </clause>
                    <clause>
                      <num value="ii">(ii)</num>
                      <p>the trust shall not contain any asset the holding of which by an interested party is prohibited by any law or regulation;</p>
                    </clause>
                    <clause>
                      <num value="iii">(iii)</num>
                      <p>the trustee shall promptly notify the reporting individual and his supervising ethics office when the holdings of any particular asset transferred to the trust by any interested party are disposed of or when the value of such holding is less than $1,000;</p>
                    </clause>
                    <clause>
                      <num value="iv">(iv)</num>
                      <p>the trust tax return shall be prepared by the trustee or his designee, and such return and any information relating thereto (other than the trust income summarized in appropriate categories necessary to complete an interested party’s tax return), shall not be disclosed to any interested party;</p>
                    </clause>
                    <clause>
                      <num value="v">(v)</num>
                      <p>an interested party shall not receive any report on the holdings and sources of income of the trust, except a report at the end of each calendar quarter with respect to the total cash value of the interest of the interested party in the trust or the net income or loss of the trust or any reports necessary to enable the interested party to complete an individual tax return required by law or to provide the information required by subsection (a)(1) of this section, but such report shall not identify any asset or holding;</p>
                    </clause>
                    <clause>
                      <num value="vi">(vi)</num>
                      <p>except for communications which solely consist of requests for distributions of cash or other unspecified assets of the trust, there shall be no direct or indirect communication between the trustee and an interested party with respect to the trust unless such communication is in writing and unless it relates only (I) to the general financial interest and needs of the interested party (including, but not limited to, an interest in maximizing income or long-term capital gain), (II) to the notification of the trustee of a law or regulation subsequently applicable to the reporting individual which prohibits the interested party from holding an asset, which notification directs that the asset not be held by the trust, or (III) to directions to the trustee to sell all of an asset initially placed in the trust by an interested party which in the determination of the reporting individual creates a conflict of interest or the appearance thereof due to the subsequent assumption of duties by the reporting individual (but nothing herein shall require any such direction); and</p>
                    </clause>
                    <clause>
                      <num value="vii">(vii)</num>
                      <p>the interested parties shall make no effort to obtain information with respect to the holdings of the trust, including obtaining a copy of any trust tax return filed or any information relating thereto except as otherwise provided in this subsection.</p>
                    </clause>
                  </subparagraph>
                  <subparagraph>
                    <num value="D">(D)</num>
                    <p>The proposed trust instrument and the proposed trustee is approved by the reporting individual’s supervising ethics office.</p>
                  </subparagraph>
                  <subparagraph>
                    <num value="E">(E)</num>
                    <p>For purposes of this subsection, “interested party” means a reporting individual, his spouse, and any minor or dependent child; “broker” has the meaning set forth in section 3(a)(4) of the Securities and Exchange Act of 1934 (15 U.S.C. 78c(a)(4)); and “investment adviser” includes any investment adviser who, as determined under regulations prescribed by the supervising ethics office, is generally involved in his role as such an adviser in the management or control of trusts.</p>
                  </subparagraph>
                  <subparagraph>
                    <num value="F">(F)</num>
                    <p>Any trust qualified by a supervising ethics office before the effective date of title II of the Ethics Reform Act of 1989 shall continue to be governed by the law and regulations in effect immediately before such effective date.</p>
                  </subparagraph>
                </paragraph>
                <paragraph>
                  <num value="4">(4)</num><subparagraph><num value="A">(A)</num>
                    <p>An asset placed in a trust by an interested party shall be considered a financial interest of the reporting individual, for the purposes of any applicable conflict of interest statutes, regulations, or rules of the Federal Government (including section 208 of title 18, United States Code), until such time as the reporting individual is notified by the trustee that such asset has been disposed of, or has a value of less than $1,000.</p>
                  </subparagraph>
                  <subparagraph>
                    <num value="B">(B)</num><clause><num value="i">(i)</num>
                      <chapeau>The provisions of subparagraph (A) shall not apply with respect to a trust created for the benefit of a reporting individual, or the spouse, dependent child, or minor child of such a person, if the supervising ethics office for such reporting individual finds that—</chapeau>
                      <subclause>
                        <num value="I">(I)</num>
                        <p>the assets placed in the trust consist of a well-diversified portfolio of readily marketable securities;</p>
                      </subclause>
                      <subclause>
                        <num value="II">(II)</num>
                        <p>none of the assets consist of securities of entities having substantial activities in the area of the reporting individual’s primary area of responsibility;</p>
                      </subclause>
                      <subclause>
                        <num value="III">(III)</num>
                        <p>the trust instrument prohibits the trustee, notwithstanding the provisions of paragraph (3)(C) (iii) and (iv) of this subsection, from making public or informing any interested party of the sale of any securities;</p>
                      </subclause>
                      <subclause>
                        <num value="IV">(IV)</num>
                        <p>the trustee is given power of attorney, notwithstanding the provisions of paragraph (3)(C)(v) of this subsection, to prepare on behalf of any interested party the personal income tax returns and similar returns which may contain information relating to the trust; and</p>
                      </subclause>
                      <subclause>
                        <num value="V">(V)</num>
                        <p>except as otherwise provided in this paragraph, the trust instrument provides (or in the case of a trust established prior to the effective date of this Act which by its terms does not permit amendment, the trustee, the reporting individual, and any other interested party agree in writing) that the trust shall be administered in accordance with the requirements of this subsection and the trustee of such trust meets the requirements of paragraph (3)(A).</p>
                      </subclause>
                    </clause>
                    <text class="three-star">* * *</text>
                  </subparagraph>
                </paragraph>
                <paragraph>
                  <num value="5">(5)</num><subparagraph><num value="A">(A)</num>
                    <chapeau>The reporting individual shall, within thirty days after a qualified blind trust is approved by his supervising ethics office, file with such office a copy of—</chapeau>
                    <clause>
                      <num value="i">(i)</num>
                      <p>the executed trust instrument of such trust (other than those provisions which relate to the testamentary disposition of the trust assets), and</p>
                    </clause>
                    <clause>
                      <num value="ii">(ii)</num>
                      <p>a list of the assets which were transferred to such trust, including the category of value of each asset as determined under subsection (d) of this section.</p>
                    </clause>
                    <continuation>This subparagraph shall not apply with respect to a trust meeting the requirements for being considered a qualified blind trust under paragraph (7) of this subsection.</continuation>
                  </subparagraph>
                  <subparagraph>
                    <num value="B">(B)</num>
                    <p>The reporting individual shall, within thirty days of transferring an asset (other than cash) to a previously established qualified blind trust, notify his supervising ethics office of the identity of each such asset and the category of value of each asset as determined under subsection (d) of this section.</p>
                  </subparagraph>
                  <subparagraph>
                    <num value="C">(C)</num>
                    <chapeau>Within thirty days of the dissolution of a qualified blind trust, a reporting individual shall—</chapeau>
                    <clause>
                      <num value="i">(i)</num>
                      <p>notify his supervising ethics office of such dissolution, and</p>
                    </clause>
                    <clause>
                      <num value="ii">(ii)</num>
                      <p>file with such office a copy of a list of the assets of the trust at the time of such dissolution and the category of value under subsection (d) of this section of each such asset.</p>
                    </clause>
                  </subparagraph>
                  <subparagraph>
                    <num value="D">(D)</num>
                    <p>Documents filed under subparagraphs (A), (B), and (C) of this paragraph and the lists provided by the trustee of assets placed in the trust by an interested party which have been sold shall be made available to the public in the same manner as a report is made available under section 105 and the provisions of that section shall apply with respect to such documents and lists.</p>
                  </subparagraph>
                  <subparagraph>
                    <num value="E">(E)</num>
                    <p>A copy of each written communication with respect to the trust under paragraph (3)(C)(vi) shall be filed by the person initiating the communication with the reporting individual’s supervising ethics office within five days of the date of the communication.</p>
                  </subparagraph>
                </paragraph>
                <paragraph>
                  <num value="6">(6)</num><subparagraph><num value="A">(A)</num>
                    <p>A trustee of a qualified blind trust shall not knowingly and willfully, or negligently, (i) disclose any information to an interested party with respect to such trust that may not be disclosed under paragraph (3) of this subsection; (ii) acquire any holding the ownership of which is prohibited by the trust instrument; (iii) solicit advice from any interested party with respect to such trust, which solicitation is prohibited by paragraph (3) of this subsection or the trust agreement; or (iv) fail to file any document required by this subsection.</p>
                  </subparagraph>
                  <subparagraph>
                    <num value="B">(B)</num>
                    <p>A reporting individual shall not knowingly and willfully, or negligently, (i) solicit or receive any information with respect to a qualified blind trust of which he is an interested party that may not be disclosed under paragraph (3)(C) of this subsection or (ii) fail to file any document required by this subsection.</p>
                  </subparagraph>
                  <subparagraph>
                    <num value="C">(C)</num><clause><num value="i">(i)</num>
                      <p>The Attorney General may bring a civil action in any appropriate United States district court against any individual who knowingly and willfully violates the provisions of subparagraph (A) or (B) of this paragraph. The court in which such action is brought may assess against such individual a civil penalty in any amount not to exceed $10,000.</p>
                    </clause>
                    <clause>
                      <num value="ii">(ii)</num>
                      <p>The Attorney General may bring a civil action in any appropriate United States district court against any individual who negligently violates the provisions of subparagraph (A) or (B) of this paragraph. The court in which such action is brought may assess against such individual a civil penalty in any amount not to exceed $5,000.</p>
                    </clause>
                  </subparagraph>
                </paragraph>
                <paragraph>
                  <num value="7">(7)</num>
                  <chapeau>Any trust may be considered to be a qualified blind trust if—</chapeau>
                  <subparagraph>
                    <num value="A">(A)</num>
                    <p>the trust instrument is amended to comply with the requirements of paragraph (3) or, in the case of a trust instrument which does not by its terms permit amendment, the trustee, the reporting individual, and any other interested party agree in writing that the trust shall be administered in accordance with the requirements of this subsection and the trustee of such trust meets the requirements of paragraph (3)(A); except that in the case of any interested party who is a dependent child, a parent or guardian of such child may execute the agreement referred to in this subparagraph;</p>
                  </subparagraph>
                  <subparagraph>
                    <num value="B">(B)</num>
                    <p>a copy of the trust instrument (except testamentary provisions) and a copy of the agreement referred to in subparagraph (A), and a list of the assets held by the trust at the time of approval by the supervising ethics office, including the category of value of each asset as determined under subsection (d) of this section, are filed with such office and made available to the public as provided under paragraph (5)(D) of this subsection; and</p>
                  </subparagraph>
                  <subparagraph>
                    <num value="C">(C)</num>
                    <p>the supervising ethics office determines that approval of the trust arrangement as a qualified blind trust is in the particular case appropriate to assure compliance with applicable laws and regulations.</p>
                  </subparagraph>
                </paragraph>
                <paragraph>
                  <num value="8">(8)</num>
                  <chapeau>A reporting individual shall not be required to report the financial interests held by a widely held investment fund (whether such fund is a mutual fund, regulated investment company, pension or deferred compensation plan, or other investment fund), if—</chapeau>
                  <subparagraph>
                    <num value="A">(A)</num><clause><num value="i">(i)</num>
                      <p>the fund is publicly traded; or</p>
                    </clause>
                    <clause>
                      <num value="ii">(ii)</num>
                      <p>the assets of the fund are widely diversified; and</p>
                    </clause>
                  </subparagraph>
                  <subparagraph>
                    <num value="B">(B)</num>
                    <p>the reporting individual neither exercises control over nor has the ability to exercise control over the financial interests held by the fund.</p>
                  </subparagraph>
                </paragraph>
              </subsection>
              <subsection>
                <num value="g">(g)</num>
                <p>Political campaign funds, including campaign receipts and expenditures, need not be included in any report filed pursuant to this title.</p>
              </subsection>
              <subsection>
                <num value="h">(h)</num>
                <p>A report filed pursuant to subsection (a), (d), or (e) of section 101 need not contain the information described in subparagraphs (A), (B), and (C) of subsection (a)(2) with respect to gifts and reimbursements received in a period when the reporting individual was not an officer or employee of the Federal Government.</p>
              </subsection>
              <subsection>
                <num value="i">(i)</num>
                <chapeau>A reporting individual shall not be required under this title to report—</chapeau>
                <paragraph>
                  <num value="1">(1)</num>
                  <chapeau>financial interests in or income derived from—</chapeau>
                  <subparagraph>
                    <num value="A">(A)</num>
                    <p>any retirement system under title 5, United States Code (including the Thrift Savings Plan under subchapter III of chapter 84 of such title); or</p>
                  </subparagraph>
                  <subparagraph>
                    <num value="B">(B)</num>
                    <p>any other retirement system maintained by the United States for officers or employees of the United States, including the President, or for members of the uniformed services; or</p>
                  </subparagraph>
                </paragraph>
                <paragraph>
                  <num value="2">(2)</num>
                  <p>benefits received under the Social Security Act.</p>
                </paragraph>
              </subsection>
            </section>
            <crossHeading>filing of reports</crossHeading>
            <section>
              <num value="103">Sec. 103.</num>
              <subsection>
                <num value="a">(a)</num>
                <p>Except as otherwise provided in this section, the reports required under this title shall be filed by the reporting individual with the designated agency ethics official at the agency by which he is employed (or in the case of an individual described in section 101(e), was employed) or in which he will serve. The date any report is received (and the date of receipt of any supplemental report) shall be noted on such report by such official.</p>
              </subsection>
              <text class="three-star">* * *</text>
              <subsection>
                <num value="g">(g)</num>
                <p>Each supervising Ethics Office shall develop and make available forms for reporting the information required by this title.</p>
              </subsection>
              <subsection>
                <num value="h">(h)</num><paragraph><num value="1">(1)</num>
                  <chapeau>The reports required under this title shall be filed by a reporting individual with—</chapeau>
                  <subparagraph>
                    <num value="A">(A)</num><clause><num value="i">(i)</num><subclause><num value="I">(I)</num>
                        <p>the Clerk of the House of Representatives, in the case of a Representative in Congress, a Delegate to Congress, the Resident Commissioner from Puerto Rico, an officer or employee of the Congress whose compensation is disbursed by the Clerk of the House of Representatives, an officer or employee of the Architect of the Capitol, United States Capitol Police, the United States Botanic Garden, the Congressional Budget Office, the Government Publishing Office, the Library of Congress, or the Copyright Royalty Tribunal (including any individual terminating service, under section 101(e), in any office or position referred to in this subclause), or an individual described in section 101(c) who is a candidate for nomination or election as a Representative in Congress, a Delegate to Congress, or the Resident Commissioner from Puerto Rico;</p>
                      </subclause>
                      <text class="three-star">* * *</text>
                    </clause>
                    <clause>
                      <num value="ii">(ii)</num>
                      <chapeau>in the case of an officer or employee of the Congress as described under section 101(f)(10) who is employed by an agency or commission established in the legislative branch after the date of the enactment of the Ethics Reform Act of 1989—</chapeau>
                      <subclause>
                        <num value="I">(I)</num>
                        <p>the Secretary of the Senate or the Clerk of the House of Representatives, as the case may be, as designated in the statute establishing such agency or commission; or</p>
                      </subclause>
                      <subclause>
                        <num value="II">(II)</num>
                        <p>if such statute does not designate such committee, the Secretary of the Senate for agencies and commissions established in even numbered calendar years, and the Clerk of the House of Representatives for agencies and commissions established in odd numbered calendar years;</p>
                      </subclause>
                    </clause>
                  </subparagraph>
                  <text class="three-star">* * *</text>
                </paragraph>
                <paragraph>
                  <num value="2">(2)</num>
                  <p>The date any report is received (and the date of receipt of any supplemental report) shall be noted on such report by such committee.</p>
                </paragraph>
              </subsection>
              <subsection>
                <num value="i">(i)</num><paragraph><num value="1">(1)</num>
                  <p>A copy of each report filed under this title by a Member or an individual who is a candidate for the office of Member shall be sent by the Clerk of the House of Representatives or Secretary of the Senate, as the case may be, to the appropriate State officer designated under section 316(a) of the Federal Election Campaign Act of 1971 of the State represented by the Member or in which the individual is a candidate, as the case may be, within the 30-day period beginning on the day the report is filed with the Clerk or Secretary.</p>
                </paragraph>
                <paragraph>
                  <num value="2">(2)</num>
                  <p>The requirements of paragraph (1) do not apply to any report filed under this title which is filed electronically and for which there is online public access, in accordance with the systems developed by the Secretary and Sergeant at Arms of the Senate and the Clerk of the House of Representatives under section 8(b) of the Stop Trading on Congressional Knowledge Act of 2012.</p>
                </paragraph>
              </subsection>
              <subsection>
                <num value="j">(j)</num><paragraph><num value="1">(1)</num>
                  <p>A copy of each report filed under this title with the Clerk of the House of Representatives shall be sent by the Clerk to the Committee on Standards of Official Conduct of the House of Representatives within the 7-day period beginning on the day the report is filed.</p>
                </paragraph>
                <text class="three-star">* * *</text>
              </subsection>
              <subsection>
                <num value="k">(k)</num>
                <p>In carrying out their responsibilities under this title with respect to candidates for office, the Clerk of the House of Representatives and the Secretary of the Senate shall avail themselves of the assistance of the Federal Election Commission. The Commission shall make available to the Clerk and the Secretary on a regular basis a complete list of names and addresses of all candidates registered with the Commission, and shall cooperate and coordinate its candidate information and notification program with the Clerk and the Secretary to the greatest extent possible.</p>
              </subsection>
              <subsection>
                <num value="l">(l)</num>
                <chapeau>Not later than 30 days after receiving notification of any transaction required to be reported under section 102(a)(5)(B), but in no case later than 45 days after such transaction, the following persons, if required to file a report under any subsection of section 101, subject to any waivers and exclusions, shall file a report of the transaction:</chapeau>
                <text class="three-star">* * *</text>
                <paragraph>
                  <num value="9">(9)</num>
                  <p>A Member of Congress, as defined under section 109(12).</p>
                </paragraph>
                <paragraph>
                  <num value="10">(10)</num>
                  <p>An officer or employee of the Congress, as defined under section 109(13).</p>
                </paragraph>
              </subsection>
            </section>
            <crossHeading>failure to file or filing false reports</crossHeading>
            <section>
              <num value="104">Sec. 104.</num>
              <subsection>
                <num value="a">(a)</num><paragraph><num value="1">(1)</num>
                  <p>The Attorney General may bring a civil action in any appropriate United States district court against any individual who knowingly and willfully falsifies or who knowingly and willfully fails to file or report any information that such individual is required to report pursuant to section 102. The court in which such action is brought may assess against such individual a civil penalty in any amount, not to exceed $50,000.</p>
                </paragraph>
                <paragraph>
                  <num value="2">(2)</num><subparagraph><num value="A">(A)</num>
                    <chapeau>It shall be unlawful for any person to knowingly and willfully—</chapeau>
                    <clause>
                      <num value="i">(i)</num>
                      <p>falsify any information that such person is required to report under section 102; and</p>
                    </clause>
                    <clause>
                      <num value="ii">(ii)</num>
                      <p>fail to file or report any information that such person is required to report under section 102.</p>
                    </clause>
                  </subparagraph>
                  <subparagraph>
                    <num value="B">(B)</num>
                    <chapeau>Any person who—</chapeau>
                    <clause>
                      <num value="i">(i)</num>
                      <p>violates subparagraph (A)(i) shall be fined under title 18, United States Code, imprisoned for not more than 1 year, or both; and</p>
                    </clause>
                    <clause>
                      <num value="ii">(ii)</num>
                      <p>violates subparagraph (A)(ii) shall be fined under title 18, United States Code.</p>
                    </clause>
                  </subparagraph>
                </paragraph>
              </subsection>
              <subsection>
                <num value="b">(b)</num>
                <p>The head of each agency, each Secretary concerned, the Director of the Office of Government Ethics, each congressional ethics committee, or the Judicial Conference, as the case may be, shall refer to the Attorney General the name of any individual which such official or committee has reasonable cause to believe has willfully failed to file a report or has willfully falsified or willfully failed to file information required to be reported.</p>
              </subsection>
              <subsection>
                <num value="c">(c)</num>
                <p>The President, the Vice President, the Secretary concerned, the head of each agency, the Office of Personnel Management, a congressional ethics committee, and the Judicial Conference of the United States, may take any appropriate personnel or other action in accordance with applicable law or regulation against any individual failing to file a report or falsifying or failing to report information required to be reported.</p>
              </subsection>
              <subsection>
                <num value="d">(d)</num><paragraph><num value="1">(1)</num>
                  <chapeau>Any individual who files a report required to be filed under this title more than 30 days after the later of—</chapeau>
                  <subparagraph>
                    <num value="A">(A)</num>
                    <p>the date such report is required to be filed pursuant to the provisions of this title and the rules and regulations promulgated thereunder; or</p>
                  </subparagraph>
                  <subparagraph>
                    <num value="B">(B)</num>
                    <p>if a filing extension is granted to such individual under section 101(g), the last day of the filing extension period, shall, at the direction of and pursuant to regulations issued by the supervising ethics office, pay a filing fee of $200. All such fees shall be deposited in the miscellaneous receipts of the Treasury. The authority under this paragraph to direct the payment of a filing fee may be delegated by the supervising ethics office in the executive branch to other agencies in the executive branch.</p>
                  </subparagraph>
                </paragraph>
                <paragraph>
                  <num value="2">(2)</num>
                  <p>The supervising ethics office may waive the filing fee under this subsection in extraordinary circumstances.</p>
                </paragraph>
              </subsection>
            </section>
            <crossHeading>custody of and public access to reports</crossHeading>
            <section>
              <num value="105">Sec. 105.</num>
              <subsection>
                <num value="a">(a)</num>
                <p>Each agency, each supervising ethics office in the executive or judicial branch, the Clerk of the House of Representatives, and the Secretary of the Senate shall make available to the public, in accordance with subsection (b), each report filed under this title with such agency or office or with the Clerk or the Secretary of the Senate.</p>
              </subsection>
              <text class="three-star">* * *</text>
              <subsection>
                <num value="b">(b)</num><paragraph><num value="1">(1)</num>
                  <p>Except as provided in the second sentence of this subsection, each agency, each supervising ethics office in the executive or judicial branch, the Clerk of the House of Representatives, and the Secretary of the Senate shall, within thirty days after any report is received under this title by such agency or office or by the Clerk or the Secretary of the Senate, as the case may be, permit inspection of such report by or furnish a copy of such report to any person requesting such inspection or copy. With respect to any report required to be filed by May 15 of any year, such report shall be made available for public inspection within 30 calendar days after May 15 of such year or within 30 days of the date of filing of such a report for which an extension is granted pursuant to section 101(g). The agency, office, Clerk, or Secretary of the Senate, as the case may be may require a reasonable fee to be paid in any amount which is found necessary to recover the cost of reproduction or mailing of such report excluding any salary of any employee involved in such reproduction or mailing. A copy of such report may be furnished without charge or at a reduced charge if it is determined that waiver or reduction of the fee is in the public interest.</p>
                </paragraph>
                <paragraph>
                  <num value="2">(2)</num>
                  <chapeau>Notwithstanding paragraph (1), a report may not be made available under this section to any person nor may any copy thereof be provided under this section to any person except upon a written application by such person stating—</chapeau>
                  <subparagraph>
                    <num value="A">(A)</num>
                    <p>that person’s name, occupation and address;</p>
                  </subparagraph>
                  <subparagraph>
                    <num value="B">(B)</num>
                    <p>the name and address of any other person or organization on whose behalf the inspection or copy is requested; and</p>
                  </subparagraph>
                  <subparagraph>
                    <num value="C">(C)</num>
                    <p>that such person is aware of the prohibitions on the obtaining or use of the report.</p>
                  </subparagraph>
                  <continuation>Any such application shall be made available to the public throughout the period during which the report is made available to the public.</continuation>
                </paragraph>
                <paragraph>
                  <num value="3">(3)</num><subparagraph><num value="A">(A)</num>
                    <p>This section does not require the immediate and unconditional availability of reports filed by an individual described in section 109(8) or 109(10) of this Act if a finding is made by the Judicial Conference, in consultation with United States Marshals Service, that revealing personal and sensitive information could endanger that individual.</p>
                  </subparagraph>
                  <subparagraph>
                    <num value="B">(B)</num>
                    <chapeau>A report may be redacted pursuant to this paragraph only—</chapeau>
                    <clause>
                      <num value="i">(i)</num>
                      <p>to the extent necessary to protect the individual who filed the report; and</p>
                    </clause>
                    <clause>
                      <num value="ii">(ii)</num>
                      <p>for as long as the danger to such individual exists.</p>
                    </clause>
                  </subparagraph>
                  <subparagraph>
                    <num value="C">(C)</num>
                    <chapeau>The Administrative Office of the United States Courts shall submit to the Committees on the Judiciary of the House of Representatives and of the Senate and the Senate Committee on Homeland Security and Governmental Affairs and the House Committee on Oversight and Government Reform an annual report with respect to the operation of this paragraph including—</chapeau>
                    <clause>
                      <num value="i">(i)</num>
                      <p>the total number of reports redacted pursuant to this paragraph;</p>
                    </clause>
                    <clause>
                      <num value="ii">(ii)</num>
                      <p>the total number of individuals whose reports have been redacted pursuant to this paragraph; and</p>
                    </clause>
                    <clause>
                      <num value="iii">(iii)</num>
                      <p>the types of threats against individuals whose reports are redacted, if appropriate.</p>
                    </clause>
                  </subparagraph>
                  <subparagraph>
                    <num value="D">(D)</num>
                    <p>The Judicial Conference, in consultation with the Department of Justice, shall issue regulations setting forth the circumstances under which redaction is appropriate under this paragraph and the procedures for redaction.</p>
                  </subparagraph>
                  <subparagraph>
                    <num value="E">(E)</num>
                    <p>This paragraph shall expire on December 31, 2017, and apply to filings through calendar year 2017.</p>
                  </subparagraph>
                </paragraph>
              </subsection>
              <subsection>
                <num value="c">(c)</num><paragraph><num value="1">(1)</num>
                  <chapeau>It shall be unlawful for any person to obtain or use a report—</chapeau>
                  <subparagraph>
                    <num value="A">(A)</num>
                    <p>for any unlawful purpose;</p>
                  </subparagraph>
                  <subparagraph>
                    <num value="B">(B)</num>
                    <p>for any commercial purpose, other than by news and communications media for dissemination to the general public;</p>
                  </subparagraph>
                  <subparagraph>
                    <num value="C">(C)</num>
                    <p>for determining or establishing the credit rating of any individual; or</p>
                  </subparagraph>
                  <subparagraph>
                    <num value="D">(D)</num>
                    <p>for use, directly or indirectly, in the solicitation of money for any political, charitable, or other purpose.</p>
                  </subparagraph>
                </paragraph>
                <paragraph>
                  <num value="2">(2)</num>
                  <p>The Attorney General may bring a civil action against any person who obtains or uses a report for any purpose prohibited in paragraph (1) of this subsection. The court in which such action is brought may assess against such person a penalty in any amount not to exceed $10,000. Such remedy shall be in addition to any other remedy available under statutory or common law.</p>
                </paragraph>
              </subsection>
              <subsection>
                <num value="d">(d)</num><paragraph><num value="1">(1)</num>
                  <p>Any report filed with or transmitted to an agency or supervising ethics office or to the Clerk of the House of Representatives or the Secretary of the Senate pursuant to this title shall be retained by such agency or office or by the Clerk of the House of Representatives or the Secretary of the Senate, as the case may be.</p>
                </paragraph>
                <paragraph>
                  <num value="2">(2)</num>
                  <chapeau>Such report shall be made available to the public—</chapeau>
                  <subparagraph>
                    <num value="A">(A)</num>
                    <p>in the case of a Member of Congress until a date that is 6 years from the date the individual ceases to be a Member of Congress; and</p>
                  </subparagraph>
                  <subparagraph>
                    <num value="B">(B)</num>
                    <p>in the case of all other reports filed pursuant to this title, for a period of 6 years after receipt of the report.</p>
                  </subparagraph>
                </paragraph>
                <paragraph>
                  <num value="3">(3)</num>
                  <p>After the relevant time period identified under paragraph (2), the report shall be destroyed unless needed in an ongoing investigation, except that in the case of an individual who filed the report pursuant to section 101(b) and was not subsequently confirmed by the Senate, or who filed the report pursuant to section 101(c) and was not subsequently elected, such reports shall be destroyed 1 year after the individual either is no longer under consideration by the Senate or is no longer a candidate for nomination or election to the Office of President, Vice President, or as a Member of Congress, unless needed in an ongoing investigation or inquiry.</p>
                </paragraph>
              </subsection>
              <subsection>
                <num value="d">(d)</num>
                <p>Any report filed with or transmitted to an agency or supervising ethics office or to the Clerk of the House of Representatives or the Secretary of the Senate pursuant to this title shall be retained by such agency or office or by the Clerk or the Secretary of the Senate, as the case may be. Such report shall be made available to the public for a period of six years after receipt of the report. After such six-year period the report shall be destroyed unless needed in an ongoing investigation, except that in the case of an individual who filed the report pursuant to section 101(b) and was not subsequently confirmed by the Senate, or who filed the report pursuant to section 101(c) and was not subsequently elected, such reports shall be destroyed one year after the individual either is no longer under consideration by the Senate or is no longer a candidate for nomination or election to the Office of President, Vice President, or as a Member of Congress, unless needed in an ongoing investigation.</p>
              </subsection>
            </section>
            <crossHeading>review of reports</crossHeading>
            <section>
              <num value="106">Sec. 106.</num>
              <subsection>
                <num value="a">(a)</num><paragraph><num value="1">(1)</num>
                  <p>Each designated agency ethics official or Secretary concerned shall make provisions to ensure that each report filed with him under this title is reviewed within sixty days after the date of such filing, except that the Director of the Office of Government Ethics shall review only those reports required to be transmitted to him under this title within sixty days after the date of transmittal.</p>
                </paragraph>
                <paragraph>
                  <num value="2">(2)</num>
                  <p>Each congressional ethics committee and the Judicial Conference shall make provisions to ensure that each report filed under this title is reviewed within sixty days after the date of such filing.</p>
                </paragraph>
              </subsection>
              <subsection>
                <num value="b">(b)</num><paragraph><num value="1">(1)</num>
                  <p>If after reviewing any report under subsection (a), the Director of the Office of Government Ethics, the Secretary concerned, the designated agency ethics official, a person designated by the congressional ethics committee, or a person designated by the Judicial Conference, as the case may be, is of the opinion that on the basis of information contained in such report the individual submitting such report is in compliance with applicable laws and regulations, he shall state such opinion on the report, and shall sign such report.</p>
                </paragraph>
                <paragraph>
                  <num value="2">(2)</num>
                  <chapeau>If the Director of the Office of Government Ethics, the Secretary concerned, the designated agency ethics official, a person designated by the congressional ethics committee, or a person designated by the Judicial Conference, after reviewing any report under subsection (a)—</chapeau>
                  <subparagraph>
                    <num value="A">(A)</num>
                    <p>believes additional information is required to be submitted, he shall notify the individual submitting such report what additional information is required and the time by which it must be submitted, or</p>
                  </subparagraph>
                  <subparagraph>
                    <num value="B">(B)</num>
                    <p>is of the opinion, on the basis of information submitted, that the individual is not in compliance with applicable laws and regulations, he shall notify the individual, afford a reasonable opportunity for a written or oral response, and after consideration of such response, reach an opinion as to whether or not, on the basis of information submitted, the individual is in compliance with such laws and regulations.</p>
                  </subparagraph>
                </paragraph>
                <paragraph>
                  <num value="3">(3)</num>
                  <chapeau>If the Director of the Office of Government Ethics, the Secretary concerned, the designated agency ethics official, a person designated by a congressional ethics committee, or a person designated by the Judicial Conference, reaches an opinion under paragraph (2)(B) that an individual is not in compliance with applicable laws and regulations, the official or committee shall notify the individual of that opinion and, after an opportunity for personal consultation (if practicable), determine and notify the individual of which steps, if any, would in the opinion of such official or committee be appropriate for assuring compliance with such laws and regulations and the date by which such steps should be taken. Such steps may include, as appropriate—</chapeau>
                  <subparagraph>
                    <num value="A">(A)</num>
                    <p>divestiture,</p>
                  </subparagraph>
                  <subparagraph>
                    <num value="B">(B)</num>
                    <p>restitution,</p>
                  </subparagraph>
                  <subparagraph>
                    <num value="C">(C)</num>
                    <p>the establishment of a blind trust,</p>
                  </subparagraph>
                  <subparagraph>
                    <num value="D">(D)</num>
                    <p>request for an exemption under section 208(b) of title 18, United States Code, or</p>
                  </subparagraph>
                  <subparagraph>
                    <num value="E">(E)</num>
                    <p>voluntary request for transfer, reassignment, limitation of duties, or resignation.</p>
                  </subparagraph>
                  <continuation>The use of any such steps shall be in accordance with such rules or regulations as the supervising ethics office may prescribe.</continuation>
                </paragraph>
                <paragraph>
                  <num value="4">(4)</num>
                  <p>If steps for assuring compliance with applicable laws and regulations are not taken by the date set under paragraph (3) by an individual in a position in the executive branch (other than in the Foreign Service or the uniformed services), appointment to which requires the advice and consent of the Senate, the matter shall be referred to the President for appropriate action.</p>
                </paragraph>
                <paragraph>
                  <num value="5">(5)</num>
                  <p>If steps for assuring compliance with applicable laws and regulations are not taken by the date set under paragraph (3) by a member of the Foreign Service or the uniformed services, the Secretary concerned shall take appropriate action.</p>
                </paragraph>
                <paragraph>
                  <num value="6">(6)</num>
                  <p>If steps for assuring compliance with applicable laws and regulations are not taken by the date set under paragraph (3) by any other officer or employee, the matter shall be referred to the head of the appropriate agency, the congressional ethics committee, or the Judicial Conference, for appropriate action; except that in the case of the Postmaster General or Deputy Postmaster General, the Director of the Office of Government Ethics shall recommend to the Governors of the Board of Governors of the United States Postal Service the action to be taken.</p>
                </paragraph>
                <paragraph>
                  <num value="7">(7)</num>
                  <p>Each supervising ethics office may render advisory opinions interpreting this title within its respective jurisdiction. Notwithstanding any other provision of law, the individual to whom a public advisory opinion is rendered in accordance with this paragraph, and any other individual covered by this title who is involved in a fact situation which is indistinguishable in all material aspects, and who acts in good faith in accordance with the provisions and findings of such advisory opinion shall not, as a result of such act, be subject to any penalty or sanction provided by this title.</p>
                </paragraph>
              </subsection>
            </section>
            <crossHeading>confidential reports and other additional requirements</crossHeading>
            <section>
              <num value="107">Sec. 107.</num>
              <subsection>
                <num value="a">(a)</num><paragraph><num value="1">(1)</num>
                  <p>Each supervising ethics office may require officers and employees under its jurisdiction (including special Government employees as defined in section 202 of title 18, United States Code) to file confidential financial disclosure reports, in such form as the supervising ethics office may prescribe. The information required to be reported under this subsection by the officers and employees of any department or agency shall be set forth in rules or regulations prescribed by the supervising ethics office, and may be less extensive than otherwise required by this title, or more extensive when determined by the supervising ethics office to be necessary and appropriate in light of sections 202 through 209 of title 18, United States Code, regulations promulgated thereunder, or the authorized activities of such officers or employees. Any individual required to file a report pursuant to section 101 shall not be required to file a confidential report pursuant to this subsection, except with respect to information which is more extensive than information otherwise required by this title. Subsections (a), (b), and (d) of section 105 shall not apply with respect to any such report.</p>
                </paragraph>
                <paragraph>
                  <num value="2">(2)</num>
                  <p>Any information required to be provided by an individual under this subsection shall be confidential and shall not be disclosed to the public.</p>
                </paragraph>
                <paragraph>
                  <num value="3">(3)</num>
                  <p>Nothing in this subsection exempts any individual otherwise covered by the requirement to file a public financial disclosure report under this title from such requirement.</p>
                </paragraph>
              </subsection>
              <subsection>
                <num value="b">(b)</num>
                <p>The provisions of this title requiring the reporting of information shall supersede any general requirement under any other provision of law or regulation with respect to the reporting of information required for purposes of preventing conflicts of interest or apparent conflicts of interest. Such provisions of this title shall not supersede the requirements of section 7342 of title 5, United States Code.</p>
              </subsection>
              <subsection>
                <num value="c">(c)</num>
                <p>Nothing in this Act requiring reporting of information shall be deemed to authorize the receipt of income, gifts, or reimbursements; the holding of assets, liabilities, or positions; or the participation in transactions that are prohibited by law, Executive order, rule, or regulation.</p>
              </subsection>
            </section>
            <crossHeading>authority of comptroller general</crossHeading>
            <section>
              <num value="108">Sec. 108.</num>
              <subsection>
                <num value="a">(a)</num>
                <p>The Comptroller General shall have access to financial disclosure reports filed under this title for the purposes of carrying out his statutory responsibilities.</p>
              </subsection>
              <subsection>
                <num value="b">(b)</num>
                <p>No later than December 31, 1992, and regularly thereafter, the Comptroller General shall conduct a study to determine whether the provisions of this title are being carried out effectively.</p>
              </subsection>
            </section>
            <crossHeading>definitions</crossHeading>
            <section>
              <num value="109">Sec. 109.</num>
              <chapeau>For the purposes of this title, the term—</chapeau>
              <paragraph>
                <num value="1">(1)</num>
                <p>“congressional ethics committees” means the Select Committee on Ethics of the Senate and the Committee on Standards of Official Conduct of the House of Representatives;</p>
              </paragraph>
              <paragraph>
                <num value="2">(2)</num>
                <chapeau>“dependent child” means, when used with respect to any reporting individual, any individual who is a son, daughter, stepson, or stepdaughter and who—</chapeau>
                <subparagraph>
                  <num value="A">(A)</num>
                  <p>is unmarried and under age 21 and is living in the household of such reporting individual; or</p>
                </subparagraph>
                <subparagraph>
                  <num value="B">(B)</num>
                  <p>is a dependent of such reporting individual within the meaning of section 152 of the Internal Revenue Code of 1986;</p>
                </subparagraph>
              </paragraph>
              <paragraph>
                <num value="3">(3)</num>
                <p>“designated agency ethics official” means an officer or employee who is designated to administer the provisions of this title within an agency;</p>
              </paragraph>
              <text class="three-star">* * *</text>
              <paragraph>
                <num value="5">(5)</num>
                <chapeau>“gift” means a payment, advance, forbearance, rendering, or deposit of money, or any thing of value, unless consideration of equal or greater value is received by the donor, but does not include—</chapeau>
                <subparagraph>
                  <num value="A">(A)</num>
                  <p>bequest and other forms of inheritance;</p>
                </subparagraph>
                <subparagraph>
                  <num value="B">(B)</num>
                  <p>suitable mementos of a function honoring the reporting individual;</p>
                </subparagraph>
                <subparagraph>
                  <num value="C">(C)</num>
                  <p>food, lodging, transportation, and entertainment provided by a foreign government within a foreign country or by the United States Government, the District of Columbia, or a State or local government or political subdivision thereof;</p>
                </subparagraph>
                <subparagraph>
                  <num value="D">(D)</num>
                  <p>food and beverages which are not consumed in connection with a gift of overnight lodging;</p>
                </subparagraph>
                <subparagraph>
                  <num value="E">(E)</num>
                  <p>communications to the offices of a reporting individual, including subscriptions to newspapers and periodicals; or</p>
                </subparagraph>
                <subparagraph>
                  <num value="F">(F)</num>
                  <p>consumable products provided by home-State businesses to the offices of a reporting individual who is an elected official, if those products are intended for consumption by persons other than such reporting individual;</p>
                </subparagraph>
              </paragraph>
              <paragraph>
                <num value="6">(6)</num>
                <p>“honoraria” has the meaning given such term in section 505 of this Act;</p>
              </paragraph>
              <paragraph>
                <num value="7">(7)</num>
                <p>“income” means all income from whatever source derived, including but not limited to the following items: compensation for services, including fees, commissions, and similar items; gross income derived from business (and net income if the individual elects to include it); gains derived from dealings in property; interest; rents; royalties; dividends; annuities; income from life insurance and endowment contracts; pensions; income from discharge of indebtedness; distributive share of partnership income; and income from an interest in an estate or trust;</p>
              </paragraph>
              <text class="three-star">* * *</text>
              <paragraph>
                <num value="11">(11)</num>
                <chapeau>“legislative branch” includes—</chapeau>
                <subparagraph>
                  <num value="A">(A)</num>
                  <p>the Architect of the Capitol;</p>
                </subparagraph>
                <subparagraph>
                  <num value="B">(B)</num>
                  <p>the Botanic Gardens;</p>
                </subparagraph>
                <subparagraph>
                  <num value="C">(C)</num>
                  <p>the Congressional Budget Office;</p>
                </subparagraph>
                <subparagraph>
                  <num value="D">(D)</num>
                  <p>the Government Accountability Office;</p>
                </subparagraph>
                <subparagraph>
                  <num value="E">(E)</num>
                  <p>the Government Publishing Office;</p>
                </subparagraph>
                <subparagraph>
                  <num value="F">(F)</num>
                  <p>the Library of Congress;</p>
                </subparagraph>
                <subparagraph>
                  <num value="G">(G)</num>
                  <p>the United States Capitol Police;</p>
                </subparagraph>
                <subparagraph>
                  <num value="H">(H)</num>
                  <p>the Office of Technology Assessment; and</p>
                </subparagraph>
                <subparagraph>
                  <num value="I">(I)</num>
                  <p>any other agency, entity, office, or commission established in the legislative branch;</p>
                </subparagraph>
              </paragraph>
              <paragraph>
                <num value="12">(12)</num>
                <p>“Member of Congress” means a United States Senator, a Representative in Congress, a Delegate to Congress, or the Resident Commissioner from Puerto Rico;</p>
              </paragraph>
              <paragraph>
                <num value="13">(13)</num>
                <chapeau>“officer or employee of the Congress” means—</chapeau>
                <subparagraph>
                  <num value="A">(A)</num>
                  <p>any individual described under subparagraph (B), other than a Member of Congress or the Vice President, whose compensation is disbursed by the Secretary of the Senate or the Clerk of the House of Representatives;</p>
                </subparagraph>
                <subparagraph>
                  <num value="B">(B)</num><clause><num value="i">(i)</num>
                    <p>each officer or employee of the legislative branch (except any officer or employee of the Government Accountability Office) who, for at least 60 days, occupies a position for which the rate of basic pay is equal to or greater than 120 percent of the minimum rate of basic pay payable for GS-15 of the General Schedule;</p>
                  </clause>
                  <clause>
                    <num value="ii">(ii)</num>
                    <p>each officer or employee of the Government Accountability Office who, for at least 60 consecutive days, occupies a position for which the rate of basic pay, minus the amount of locality pay that would have been authorized under section 5304 of title 5, United States Code (had the officer or employee been paid under the General Schedule) for the locality within which the position of such officer or employee is located (as determined by the Comptroller General), is equal to or greater than 120 percent of the minimum rate of basic pay payable for GS–15 of the General Schedule; and</p>
                  </clause>
                  <clause>
                    <num value="iii">(iii)</num>
                    <p>at least one principal assistant designated for purposes of this paragraph by each Member who does not have an employee who occupies a position for which the rate of basic pay is equal to or greater than 120 percent of the minimum rate of basic pay payable for GS–15 of the General Schedule;</p>
                  </clause>
                </subparagraph>
              </paragraph>
              <paragraph>
                <num value="14">(14)</num>
                <p>“personal hospitality of any individual” means hospitality extended for a nonbusiness purpose by an individual, not a corporation or organization, at the personal residence of that individual or his family or on property or facilities owned by that individual or his family;</p>
              </paragraph>
              <paragraph>
                <num value="15">(15)</num>
                <chapeau>“reimbursement” means any payment or other thing of value received by the reporting individual, other than gifts, to cover travel-related expenses of such individual other than those which are—</chapeau>
                <subparagraph>
                  <num value="A">(A)</num>
                  <p>provided by the United States Government, the District of Columbia, or a State or local government or political subdivision thereof;</p>
                </subparagraph>
                <subparagraph>
                  <num value="B">(B)</num>
                  <p>required to be reported by the reporting individual under section 7342 of title 5, United States Code; or</p>
                </subparagraph>
                <subparagraph>
                  <num value="C">(C)</num>
                  <p>required to be reported under section 304 of the Federal Election Campaign Act of 1971 (2 U.S.C. 434);</p>
                </subparagraph>
              </paragraph>
              <paragraph>
                <num value="16">(16)</num>
                <p>“relative” means an individual who is related to the reporting individual, as father, mother, son, daughter, brother, sister, uncle, aunt, great aunt, great uncle, first cousin, nephew, niece, husband, wife, grandfather, grandmother, grandson, granddaughter, father-in-law, mother-in-law, son-in-law, daughter-in-law, brother-in-law, sister-in-law, stepfather, stepmother, stepson, stepdaughter, stepbrother, stepsister, half brother, half sister, or who is the grandfather or grandmother of the spouse of the reporting individual, and shall be deemed to include the fiance or fiancee of the reporting individual;</p>
              </paragraph>
              <text class="three-star">* * *</text>
              <paragraph>
                <num value="18">(18)</num>
                <chapeau>“supervising ethics office” means—</chapeau>
                <subparagraph>
                  <num value="A">(A)</num>
                  <p>the Senate Committee on Ethics of the Senate, for Senators, officers and employees of the Senate, and other officers or employees of the legislative branch required to file financial disclosure reports with the Secretary of the Senate pursuant to section 103(h) of this title;</p>
                </subparagraph>
                <subparagraph>
                  <num value="B">(B)</num>
                  <p>the Committee on Standards of Official Conduct of the House of Representatives, for Members, officers and employees of the House of Representatives and other officers or employees of the legislative branch required to file financial disclosure reports with the Clerk of the House of Representatives pursuant to section 103(h) of this title;</p>
                </subparagraph>
                <subparagraph>
                  <num value="C">(C)</num>
                  <p>the Judicial Conference for judicial officers and judicial employees; and</p>
                </subparagraph>
                <subparagraph>
                  <num value="D">(D)</num>
                  <p>the Office of Government Ethics for all executive branch officers and employees; and</p>
                </subparagraph>
              </paragraph>
              <paragraph>
                <num value="19">(19)</num>
                <p>“value” means a good faith estimate of the dollar value if the exact value is neither known nor easily obtainable by the reporting individual.</p>
              </paragraph>
            </section>
            <crossHeading>notice of actions taken to comply with ethics agreements</crossHeading>
            <section>
              <num value="110">Sec. 110.</num>
              <subsection>
                <num value="a">(a)</num>
                <p>In any case in which an individual agrees with that individual’s designated agency ethics official, the Office of Government Ethics, a Senate confirmation committee, a congressional ethics committee, or the Judicial Conference, to take any action to comply with this Act or any other law or regulation governing conflicts of interest of, or establishing standards of conduct applicable with respect to, officers or employees of the Government, that individual shall notify in writing the designated agency ethics official, the Office of Government Ethics, the appropriate committee of the Senate, the congressional ethics committee, or the Judicial Conference, as the case may be, of any action taken by the individual pursuant to that agreement. Such notification shall be made not later than the date specified in the agreement by which action by the individual must be taken, or not later than three months after the date of the agreement, if no date for action is so specified.</p>
              </subsection>
              <subsection>
                <num value="b">(b)</num>
                <p>If an agreement described in subsection (a) requires that the individual recuse himself or herself from particular categories of agency or other official action, the individual shall reduce to writing those subjects regarding which the recusal agreement will apply and the process by which it will be determined whether the individual must recuse himself or herself in a specific instance. An individual shall be considered to have complied with the requirements of subsection (a) with respect to such recusal agreement if such individual files a copy of the document setting forth the information described in the preceding sentence with such individual’s designated agency ethics official or the appropriate supervising ethics office within the time prescribed in the last sentence of subsection (a).</p>
              </subsection>
            </section>
            <crossHeading>administration of provisions</crossHeading>
            <section>
              <num value="111">Sec. 111.</num>
              <chapeau>The provisions of this title shall be administered by <inline name="three-star">* * *</inline>
                     </chapeau>
              <text class="three-star">* * *</text>
              <paragraph>
                <num value="2">(2)</num>
                <p>the Select Committee on Ethics of the Senate and the Committee on Standards of Official Conduct of the House of Representatives, as appropriate, with regard to officers and employees described in paragraphs (9) and (10) of section 101(f).</p>
              </paragraph>
              <text class="three-star">* * *</text>
            </section>
          </title>
        </quotedContent>
      </note>
    </level>
  </content>
</document>